Have you ever wondered which country is
closest to space? Well, it seems simple.
Or maybe not. Firstly, we need to find
the highest point on the planet and
obviously that's Everest. At almost
9,000 m above sea level, it's truly the
roof of the world. The summit of Everest
lies on the border between two
countries. So, the peak is technically
split in half. The southern slope
belongs to Nepal and the northern slope
to China. So, it seems that the
countries closest to space are Nepal and
China at the same time. But that's
wrong. You see, our planet is not
actually round. It's flat. Just kidding.
But the Earth really is not a sphere.
It's a geoid. Because of its rotation on
its axis, [music]
a centrifugal force acts on the planet,
stretching it at the equator and
flattening it at the poles. And due to
the complex terrain and uneven mass, it
isn't a perfect ellipoid. Here's an
exaggerated model of what the Earth
actually looks like with its
irregularities enlarged hundreds of
times to make the distortions visible at
this scale. The Earth's radius at the
equator is 21 km greater than at the
poles. And now we need to find the
highest point right on the equator. And
there really is one, Mount Chimberazzo,
a volcano rising over 6,000 m above sea
level in Ecuador. And if we compare the
distance from the center of the Earth to
the summits of Everest and Chimberazzo,
we'll see that Chimberazzo is 2 km
farther from the center, making Ecuador
the closest country to space.